A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 1-3254 FA739A
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Making lawyers for the world around us: assessment of a series of three grants for the Internships in Environmental Law Teaching (Reports 002249), 1972; Rabin, Robert L. (Box 92)
  Environmental law -- Study and teaching -- United States
- The national assessment of education (Reports 002250), 1969; Capelle, Jean, 1909-1983 (Box 92)
  Education -- United States
- Anthropological perspectives on primary education in Indonesia (Reports 002251), 1969; Bruner, Edward M.; Bruner, Elaine (Box 92)
  Education -- Indonesia; Educational anthropology -- Indonesia
- Criminal law training: many uses and may unresolved issues: assessment of grants to five law schools: Georgetown, New York University, Northwestern, Pennsylvania and Texas, Sept. (Reports 002252), 1971; Cochran, Robert (Box 92)
  54 p. + appendix.
  Law schools -- United States; Criminal law -- Study and teaching -- United States
- Far from perfect, but Chicano lawyers were made here: An assessment of a grant to the University of Denver for summer institutes designed to prepare Mexican-Americans for the study of law, Sept. (Reports 002253), 1970; McLean, Sheila Avrin (Box 92)
  Law -- Study and teaching -- Colorado -- Denver (Colo.); Mexican Americans -- Education -- Colorado -- Denver (Colo.)
- The Ford Foundation Program in Pakistan (Reports 002254), 1970 (Box 92)
  Philanthropy -- Pakistan
- The Ford Foundation's Program in the Changing Role of Women (Reports 002255), 1973; Giele, Janet Zollinger (Box 92)
  Overview of women's movement and possible directions for a Foundation program concerned with the needs of women and the family.
  Education and Research/National Affairs/International Division
  Women -- United States -- Social conditions; Women's rights -- United States; Family -- United States
- Human rights and intellectual freedom: Information paper, Nov. (Reports 002256), 1975; Heaps, David (Box 92)
  Human rights; Intellectual freedom; Freedom of the press
- Future Program: Education and Research Division (Reports 002257), 1975 (Box 92)
  Presents future program directions in the area of education.
  Philanthropy; Education
- A place to be, a place to learn: Assessment of a grant to the University of California at Berkeley for "Project Community" (Reports 002258), 1971; Almond, Peter (Box 92)
  Alternative education -- California -- Berkeley; Youth -- California -- Berkeley
- The National Council on Crime and Delinquency: Fifteen years of work -- and where next?, Aug. (Reports 002259), 1969; Brooks, Richard Oliver; Rubenstein, Judith S. (Judith Selig), 1942- (Box 93)
  Description of the center and the field of crime and delinquency.
  Crime -- United States; National Council on Crime and Delinquency
- Generation gap on a Southern island: an assessment of the training program at Penn Community Center, Sept. (Reports 002260), 1969; Passett, Barry A. (Box 93)
  Evaluation of a center set up to help rural African Americans learn community development techniques.
  Rural development -- Southern States; Community development -- Southern States; African Americans -- Southern States
- Hazy objectives, uncertain impact: Assessment of a grant to the National Municipal League for research and documentation on legislature reapportionment, Dec. (Reports 002261), 1971; Leonard, Rodney E. (Box 93)
  Apportionment (Election law) -- United States
- Two kinds of jungles: Evaluation of a grant to the Organization for Tropical Studies (OTS) for pilot research grants and an assessment of OTS structure and dynamics, Nov. (Reports 002262), 1971; Layne, Elizabeth N. (Box 93)
  Biology -- Tropics -- Study and teaching; Organization for Tropical Studies
- The merits and limits of dynamism: Assessment of a grant to the National Council of Negro Women to promote home ownership opportunities in the form of "Turnkey III and IV" (Reports 002263), 1973; Goldman, Clifford A.; Abeles, Peter (Box 93)
  91 p. + appendix
  Home ownership -- United States; African Americans -- Housing
- The invisible schools (Reports 002264), 1964; Saltzman, Henry (Box 93)
  Condensed from an address at the 8th Governors' Conference in Madison, Wisc. Discusses the education of poor children.
  L64-709
  Education -- United States; Poor children -- Education -- United States
- Third men in new arenas of conflict: an assessment of the work of the National Center for Dispute Settlement (American Arbitration Association) and of the Racial Negotiations Project (Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations, Wayne State University an (Reports 002265), 1970; Laue, James H. (Box 93)
  175 p. + appendices.
  Conflict management -- United States; Urban renewal -- United States
- Open America: an assessment of the work of the National Committee Against Discrimination in Housing (NCDH), Sept. (Reports 002266), 1969; Giesey, Walter (Box 93)
  Discrimination in Housing -- United States; Housing -- United States; National Committee Against Discrimination in Housing
- Trying to catch up with change: an assessment of the National Assembly for Social Policy and Development (Reports 002267), 1970; Spingarn, Natalie Davis; Goldmann, Robert, 1921- (Box 93)
  Project evaluation, Division of National Affairs.
  [ii], 48 leaves -- 28 cm.
  Social planning -- United States; Social action -- United States; National Assembly for Social Policy and Development
- An old institution in a new role: an assessment of the National Civil Service League's performance and philosophy under recent federal contracts (Reports 002268), 1970; Norwitch, Bernard E. (Box 93)
  Review of the National Civil Service League's involvement in public employment for the disadvantaged in anticipation of the Foundation funding a program in that area.
  Civil service -- United States; Minorities -- Employment -- United States; National Civil Service League
- The status of the Land Reform Program in India (Reports 002269), 1954; Ladejinsky, Wolf Isaac (Box 93)
  B-625
  Land reform -- India
- Special training program for foreign (and American) nationals (Reports 002270), 1955; Johnstone, William Crane, 1901- (Box 93)
  B-524
  Training; International education
- A new breed of entrepreneurs: an assessment of a Foundation grant to the Black Economic Union (Reports 002271), 1970; Farr, Walter G. (Box 93)
  Assessment is part of a cluster of three in the area of minority economic development being performed under a grant to New York University.
  156 p.
  African American business enterprises; African American businesspeople; Entrepreneurship -- United States
- Access to the law (Reports 002272), 1972; Ryan, Leonard Eames (Box 93)
  Remarks on "The interest of the Ford Foundation in legal services for all Americans."
  Legal services -- United States
- Summary tables: FY 1974 and earlier years (Reports 002273), 1975 (Box 93)
  Tables intended for reference on the International Division's activities in FY 1974 with earlier figures when available.
  30 p. + appendices.
  Program budgeting
- Drug addiction in Great Britain (Reports 002274), 1970; May, Edgar, 1929- (Box 93)
  Drug abuse -- Great Britain; Drug abuse treatment centers -- Great Britain; Drug abuse -- Government policy -- Great Britain
- The Public Interest Law Firm: New voices for new constituencies (Reports 002275), 1971 (Box 93)
  An analysis of the rationale, legal basis and structure of public interest law organizations, including a few case histories drawn from public interest law practices.
  Public interest law -- United States; Environmental law -- United States; Law -- Study and teaching -- United States
- International communications: activities in the developed and developing countries (Reports 002276), 1975 (Box 94)
  A discussion paper. Title sufficient as abstract.
  Telecommunications
- An examination of communications activities in the International Division for fiscal years 1973 and 1974 (Reports 002277), 1975 (Box 94)
  A supplement to the discussion paper "International communications: activities in the developed and developing countries." See report #002276.
  193 p. + appendices.
- Formative science education in Latin America. Parts 1-4 (Reports 002278), 1967; Rinaldini, Luis M. (Box 94)
  230 p.
  Education -- Latin America; Science -- Study and teaching -- Latin America
- Formative science education in Latin America (Reports 002279-001), 1967; Rinaldini, Luis M. (Box 94)
  Five parts in eight volumes.
- Not by pride alone: an assessment of the Foundation's grant to the Southwest Council of La Raza (Reports 002279-002), 1969; Kramer, H. J. (Herbert J.), 1939-; Goldmann, Robert, 1921- (Box 94)
  230 p. + appendix.
  Mexican Americans -- Economic conditions; Mexican Americans -- Social conditions; Ford Foundation. Social Development; National Council of La Raza
- The theme gets lost amid the musical chairs: Assessment of a grant to the Spindletop Research Institute for the establishment of the National Area Development Institute (Reports 002280), 1972; Leonard, Rodney E. (Box 94)
  For Singapore meeting on education held in Oct. 1970. Title sufficient as abstract.
  Education -- Congresses
- Advocacy in Dixie: Promise and problems evaluation of a grant to the South Carolina Council on Human Relations for a program of research, monitoring and advocacy in several areas of state activity (Reports 002281), 1973; Spingarn, Natalie Davis (Box 94)
  109 p. + appendices.
  Public welfare -- South Carolina
- He'd rather be Wrice: an assessment of the operations of the Young Great Society in Philadelphia (Reports 002282), 1971; Henry, Ragan (Box 94)
  Assessment of a grant to an organization established to help poor areas of Philadelphia.
  National Affairs/Urban and Metropolitan Development/Social Development
  Youth -- Pennsylvania (Pa.) -- Philadelphia (Pa.); Community development, Urban -- Pennsylvania (Pa.) -- Philadelphia (Pa.); Young Great Society
- A vague mandate, a slow start and now: A program: An assessment of a grant to Yale University for a program of Interdisciplinary Teaching and Research in Urban Law, Oct. (Reports 002283), 1971; Tufo, Peter (Box 94)
  Law -- Study and teaching -- Connecticut -- New Haven (Conn.)
- The elementary school as modernizer: a Brazilian study (Reports 002284), 1973; Holsinger, Donald B. (Box 94)
  Revised and somewhat expanded version of a paper presented at the 67th Annual Meeting of the American Sociological Association, New Orleans, Aug. 1972. Discusses childhood socialization of modern values in Brazil.
  Education, Elementary -- Brazil; Socialization -- Brazil
- Priming the federal system: An assessment of the development and work of "the big six" representing cities, countries, states and regional districts vis-a-vis the federal government with special reference to selected Foundation grants, Dec. (Reports 002285), 1972; Talbot, Allan R.; Katzowitz, Lauren (Box 94)
  Nonprofit organizations -- United States; Pressure groups -- United States
- Toward freer enterprise in construction: an assessment of grants to secure bonding for minority contractors in four cities, Dec. (Reports 002286), 1970; Grabino, Harold; Talbot, Allan R. (Box 94)
  Assessment of grants to secure bonding for minority contractors in Oakland, Cleveland, New York, and Boston.
  Contractors -- United States; Minority business enterprises -- United States
- Helping the law do its job: an assessment of the work of the Centers of Criminal Justice (Reports 002287), 1970; Cochran, Robert (Box 94)
  An assessment of four university-connected centers for research and demonstrations on reform and change in the criminal justice system.
  58 p. + appendix.
  Criminology -- Research -- United States
- Competence and esprit de corps: An assessment of a grant to the Manpower Assistance Project (MAP), Sept. (Reports 002288), 1970; Belitsky, A. Harvey (Abraham Harvey), 1929-; Sheppard, Harold L.; Stephansky, Ben S. (Box 95)
  106 p. + appendices.
  Occupational training -- United States; Manpower -- United States
- Alternative ends to a means: Assessment of a grant to the Los Angeles Technical Services Corporation for the application of aerospace systems to urban problems (Reports 002289), 1972; Goldman, Clifford A.; Rezendes, Dennis (Box 95)
  117 p. + appendix.
  Aerospace industries -- California -- Los Angeles (Calif.); Urban renewal -- California -- Los Angeles (Calif.)
- The limits of prestige: Lawyers Committee for Civil Rights under Law, Jan. (Reports 002290), 1970; Morris, Barbara (Box 95)
  121 p.
- Solid growth: But more focus needed: an assessment of a grant to the Interracial Council for Business Opportunity, Oct. (Reports 002291), 1970; Zimmerman, Anita; Zimmerman, Stanley (Box 95)
  One of a series of evaluations of minority economic development programs conducted under a grant to New York University.
  Minorities -- United States -- Economic conditions; Minority business enterprises -- United States
- Too few try to do too much with too little: Assessment of a grant to the International Union for the Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources (IUCR) (Reports 002292), 1972; May, Edgar, 1929- (Box 95)
  Environmental protection; Conservation of natural resources; International Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources
- Tomorrow's policeman: an appraisal of the International Association of Chiefs of Police, Nov. (Reports 002293), 1969; Sullivan, James. (Box 95)
  Assesses a grant to improve police training and stature.
  Police -- Training of -- United States
- Professionalizing an old profession: Assessment of a grant to the Institute of Politics, with operations in New Orleans, Mississippi and Arkansas (Reports 002294), 1972; Walls, Dwayne E. (Box 95)
  Assessment of a grant designed to encourage capable young people to enter the political arena in the south.
  63 p. + appendices (Page 1 missing)
  Political science -- Study and teaching -- United States
- The small-town crier: an assessment of the work of the Micro-City Project at St. John's University (Reports 002295), 1970; Roush, J. Edward (John Edward), 1920-2004 (Box 95)
  Assessment of a grant to improve life in small cities.
  Small town crier
  Cities and towns -- United States; Community development -- United States
- The Ford Foundation programs and developing federal activities (Reports 002296), 1965 (Box 95)
  Paper briefly outlines major types of grants made by each of Foundation's Program and lists a number of federal activities related to each program.
  Education;Special Projects;Public Affairs;Economic Development and Administration;International Training and Research;Humanities and the Arts;Science and Engineering;Overseas Division;Population Program;International Affairs
  Philanthropy; Government programs -- United States
- The politics of saving nature: An assessment of the performance of the Conservation Service Center of the Massachusetts Audubon Society, Oct. (Reports 002297), 1969; Ogburn, Charlton, 1911-1998 (Box 95)
  Conservation of natural resources -- Massachusetts; Environmental protection -- Massachusetts
- Pattern for social change: An evaluation of the MARC Fellowship/Internship Program, Aug. (Reports 002298), 1969; Mack, Raymond W.; Sylvester, Edward (Box 95)
  Assessment of the Metropolitan Applied Research Center, which was established to assist the poor in northern cities.
  81 p. + appendices.
  Poor -- United States; African Americans; Urban renewal -- United States
- Planning of an English language project (Reports 002299), 1965; Payne, Richard M. (Box 95)
  A how-to manual on planning English language projects.
  English language -- Study and teaching -- Developing countries -- Foreign speakers
- Ford Foundation activities in English as a second language to (Reports 002300), 1965; Ward, F. Champion (Box 95)
  Prepared as background information for the Ditchley Conference on ESL, November 1965.
  12 p. + appendices.
  English language -- Study and teaching -- Foreign speakers
- Employment process in developing countries: Papers for a seminar sponsored by the Ford Foundation (Reports 002301), 1973; Bruton, Henry J. (Box 96)
  2 v.
  Conference papers (1973 Feb. 21-23: Bogota, Colombia)
- The Academic Administration Internship Program for Mexico and Central America: Evaluation study (Reports 002302), 1971; Peña, Guillermo de la; Socolow, Daniel J., 1940-; Netherton, John P. (Box 96)
  06900684
  Internship programs -- Mexico; Universities and colleges -- Mexico -- Administration; University of California (System). Regents
- Ford Foundation activities in teaching English as a second language (Reports 002303), 1962; Quinn, John A. (Box 96, Reel R-9302)
  International Affairs;International Training and Research;Overseas Development
  Ford Foundation activities in teaching English as a second language
  English language -- Study and teaching -- Foreign speakers; Education -- Developing countries
- Ford Foundation activities in teaching English as a second language: report of an Inter-Program Committee, February 1964: last version of report (Reports 002304), Ward, F. Champion; Quinn, John A. (Box 96)
  English language -- Study and teaching -- Foreign speakers; English language -- Study and teaching -- Foreign countries; Education -- Developing countries
- Observations relating to English language training in Nigeria based on a short visit to Nigeria, March 23-April 4, 1964 (Reports 002305), Jacobs, Robert (Box 96)
  Discussion of a grant made to Southern Illinois University for the development of intensive English training programs in the civil service training centers located in the major political regions of Nigeria.
  33 p. + appendices.
  English language -- Study and teaching -- Nigeria -- Foreign speakers
- Diffusion of English in Japan (Reports 002306), 1966; Passin, Herbert (Box 96)
  Memorandum of an all-day meeting held on the diffusion of the English language in Japan.
  English language -- Study and teaching -- Japan -- Foreign speakers
- Notes on English as a second language as related to Africa (Reports 002307), 1961; Fox, Melvin J. (Box 96)
  Memorandum prepared for IIE Interim Committee on Educational Exchange with Africa with attachment "American ESL overseas programs."
  English language -- Study and teaching -- Africa -- Foreign speakers
- Arts and sciences program: The continuing role of the university (Reports 002308), 1962; McPeak, William Wallace (Box 96)
  Outlines some factors which tend to distract the universities from their primary mission and some actions the Foundation might take to help meet this problem.
  Education, Higher -- United States; Universities and colleges -- United States
- Special study of English language teaching problems and needs in Nigeria: a preliminary report to the Ford Foundation (Reports 002309), 1966; Jacobs, Robert (Box 96)
  A preliminary report to the Ford Foundation. For final report see: Report #001078. Title sufficient as abstract.
- The current and potential supply of trained personnel in ESL (Reports 002310), 1964; Fox, Melvin J. (Box 96)
- Report on Passin-Stone trip to Japan (Reports 002311), 1962; Passin, Herbert (Box 96)
  Report of a trip largely to study cooperation in Japan.
  International cooperation; Philanthropy -- Japan
- English language teaching in Algeria: Report on a survey conducted in relation to the establishment of Modern Language Institutes (Reports 002312), 1975; Mize, David W.; Ohannessian, Sirarpi; Tucker, G. Richard (Box 96)
  English language -- Study and teaching -- Algeria -- Foreign speakers
- Indonesia: English language activities (Reports 002313), 1968 (Box 96)
- Report to Chairman National Commission on Manpower and Education Government of Pakistan (Reports 002314), 1969; Lohmann, M. R. (Box 96)
  Report on technical and engineering education in Pakistan.
  06800717
  Industrialization -- Pakistan; Technical education -- Pakistan; Occupational training -- Pakistan; University of California (System). Regents
- Report on visit to Indonesia March 9 to April 10 (Reports 002315), 1970; Beeby, C. E. (Clarence Edward), 1902-1998 (Box 96)
  Discusses observations on education and manpower made on a visit to Indonesia.
  Education -- Indonesia; Manpower -- Indonesia
- Getting organized in the Far North: an assessment of a grant to the Alaska Federation of Natives Charitable Trust, Feb. (Reports 002316), 1971; Wolfe, Herman. (Box 96)
  Assessment of a grant designed to help train native Alaskans as leaders.
  Indians of North America -- Alaska; Leadership
- Public and private support for the development of minority and poverty group-owned businesses: A study with special emphasis on the role of foundations, Jan. (Reports 002317), 1975; Goodman, Felice M.; Spellun, Arnold (Box 96)
  Study attempts to chronicle a perspective of foundation efforts in support of minority-owned business ventures within the framework of other major efforts, public and private.
  94 p. + appendices.
  Minority business enterprises -- United States
- Long years' journey into the suburbs: An assessment of a series of grants to organizations in Cleveland, Ohio, Washington, D.C. and Denver, Colorado to open the housing market to minority homeseekers (Reports 002318), 1973; Goldman, Clifford A.; Stabler, Elizabeth, 1905-1985 (Box 96)
  Evaluation of Foundation grants to three fair-housing projects.
  Discrimination in housing -- Ohio -- Cleveland; Discrimination in housing -- Washington (D.C.); Discrimination in housing -- Colorado -- Denver (Colo.)
- The fallowing years: an assessment of the John F. Kennedy Institute, Jan. (Reports 002319), 1972; Clemow, Bice (Box 96)
  136 p. + appendices.
  Political science -- Study and teaching -- United States; Universities and colleges -- United States; John F. Kennedy-Institut für Nordamerikastudien
- A proven formula: but could it prove more?: evaluation of a series of grants to the American Assembly at Columbia University, Nov. (Reports 002320), 1972; Clemow, Bice (Box 97)
  National Affairs/Social Development/Government and Law
  83 p. + appendices.
  Universities and colleges -- United States; American Assembly
- The unsettled settlement house: An evaluation of the Westminster Neighborhood Association, Inc. in Los Angeles's Watts community, Aug. (Reports 002321), 1969; Mitchell, Gordon, 1923-2003 (Box 97)
  Social settlements -- California -- Los Angeles (Calif.); Housing -- California -- Los Angeles (Calif.)
- Competence and impact: and now for a strategy: assessment of grants to the Center for National Policy Review, Sept. (Reports 002322), 1973; Price, Hugh B. (Box 97)
  Assessment of grants to the Center for National Policy Review, an organization assisting civil rights groups in pressing for the implementation of equal opportunity laws and policies in government.
  44 p. + appendices.
- The rewards and hazards of research grants: an assessment of twelve grants for studies relating to the political process (Reports 002323), 1974; Conrad, Roan (Box 97)
  157 p. + appendices.
  Political science -- Research -- United States
- Whither these resources?: An evaluation of the performance of Resources for the Future under a series of general support and special projects grants from this Foundation, Feb. (Reports 002324), 1973; Deutch, John M., 1938- (Box 97)
  Evaluation of Resources for the Future, an organization set up for research and education in the field of natural resources.
  National Affairs/Research & Education/Latin America and the Caribbean
  Conservation of natural resources -- United States; Resources for the Future
- An evaluation of the General Development Grant and the staff development grants of the Ford Foundation to the University of Ibadan 1958-1972 (Reports 002325), 1973; Pratt, Cranford; Swanson, John E.; Bigelow, Ross Edgar (Box 97)
  06100210
  61 p. + appendices.
  Education, Higher -- Nigeria; University of Ibadan